My chakra is reacting strongly.
(アシュラ)俺のチャクラが
すごく反応してる。
(カンナ)これは？
What's that?
(アシュラ)さっきの病人たちに
生えていたのは これだ。
It's what was growing on
the sick people.
そうか 神樹の樹液が
大地に染み出してるんだ。
I see!
The sap from the Divine Tree's
seeped into the soil.
たぶん この樹液が栄養となり→
The sap acts like a fertilizer,
荒野のど真ん中に オアシスを
作り出してるんだ。
making this area a lush oasis in
the middle of such a barren region.
(タイゾウ)神樹の力が土地を
豊かにしてるってのか？
The power of the Divine Tree
is making the land fertile?
うん。
それじゃ 神樹は→
So…is the Divine Tree
getting its power back?
力を取り戻してきてる？
いや。
No, it hasn't completely revived…
まだ完全に
蘇生してるわけじゃない。
でも 徐々によみがえるだろうね。
But it probably will eventually.
問題は それより…。
But the real problem is…
何だよ？
Is what?
人間のほうが先に
汚染されると思う。
The people are becoming
contaminated first.
汚染？
ああ 神樹の樹液は→
Contaminated?!
The people and animals eat
the produce grown on this land,
この地の作物から
それを食べる動物や人間に→
which accumulates
the sap of the Divine Tree.
どんどん蓄積される。
ってことは→
So does that mean…
ここの食い物食うと
あの病気にかかるってことかよ。
If you eat the food here,
you're gonna get sick?
たぶん。
オエッ！
Probably.
俺 昨日 思いっきり
食っちまったぜ！
But I ate so much yesterday!
大丈夫だよ 少しくらいなら
俺の術でも治せる。
It's all right. My jutsu can
take care of a small amount…
でも 長年 蓄積されたものは…。
But if you keep ingesting and
accumulating it for many years…
でもよ ここの警備を
長老がやらせてたってことは→
Since the Village Elder ordered
for this place to be under watch,
長老は全部 知ってる
ってことじゃねえのか？
does that means
he knows everything?
そうなるね。
So it seems.
Ashura's Decision
そうか 神樹を見たのか。
はい。
I see…
You saw the Divine Tree.
Yes.
旅の者よ なぜお前は
そこまで村の秘密を探るのだ？
Traveler, why do you keep digging
for our village secrets?
Forgive me.
すみません 実は俺→
I'm from the Village of Ninshu
and was told to come here.
忍宗の里から ここへ
来るように言われたんです。
忍宗？
Ninshu?
The Ninshu that destroyed
the land 20 years ago…
20年前 大地を滅ぼしたという…。
お前は その一門か？
はい。
You are a pupil?
Yes.
あの樹は
地上を破滅に追いやった→
That tree is the ruin of the specter
that almost destroyed our world.
もののけの残骸です
だから 力があるのです。
That is why it's so powerful.
私は それをなんとかするように
言いつかってきました。
I've been ordered to do
something about it.
長老 いわば あの樹は麻薬です。
Lord Elder, to be blunt,
that tree is a narcotic.
The power of the Divine Tree is
indeed making this land abundant,
神樹の力は確かに
土地を豊かにします。
ですが 同時に村人たちを
蝕んでもいる。
but it's also affecting
the villagers adversely.
このままでは いずれ…。
At this rate…
旅の者よ それは
気づいていたことじゃ。
Traveler,
I am already aware of that.
But I cannot authorize
that tree's destruction.
だが あの樹をなくすことは→
許可できぬ。
なぜです？
Why is that?
あの樹が力を持ち始めたのは→
That tree started to grow powerfully
several decades ago.
今から十数年ほど前じゃ。
それまで この地は
荒れ果てた土地じゃった。
Until then,
this was arid and barren land.
We had terrible droughts
nearly every year.
容赦ない干ばつが
毎年のように襲い→
数え切れぬほどの
餓死者を出してきた。
I've lost count of how many
died of starvation.
だったら 井戸を掘ってみては？
Why don't you try digging a well?
It was futile…
ムダだった。
だった？
"Was"?
とっくにそんなことは試した。
We tried ages ago.
だが 何年掘ろうと
この土地に横たわる固い岩盤が→
One could dig for years,
only to hit the solid bedrock
that runs across this land.
それを拒んでおるのだ。
今 あの樹を失えば
我々は どうなる？
If we cut down that tree now,
what will happen to us?
村の者たちに
飢えに怯える日々に戻れなど→
I cannot tell the villagers
that we will be returning to
those days of hunger and suffering.
わしには とうてい言えぬ。
それに たとえ事実を知っても→
Besides, even if I told them the truth,
the villagers will not believe me.
村人たちは賛同しまい。
旅の者よ わしらに
これ以上 かかわるな。
Traveler, do not get involved
any further…
早々にこの地を立ち去るがよい。
It would be best if you leave
as soon as possible.
カンナ キミはどう思う？
Kanna, how do you feel?
どう思うって。
About what?
キミも このままでは
いつかは神樹に汚染される。
In time, you will become infected
by the Divine Tree.
And?
We have no other choice!
だからって
どうしようもないじゃない！
私たちには この土地以外に
行くあてなんてない。
There's nowhere else for us to go!
ただ 我慢するしかないのよ。
We just have to endure
and live with it.
皆さん 聞いてください。
Please listen, everyone!
Do you know the truth
behind the Divine Tree?
皆さんは知ってるんですか？
神樹の真実を。
お おいアシュラ。
Hey, Ashura!
(アシュラ)神樹は
もののけの残骸です。
The Divine Tree is
the ruins of a specter.
療養所の病気の原因は
丘にある神樹なんです。
The Divine Tree is the cause
of the illness afflicting
the people at the clinic.
神樹の力に頼り続ければ
いずれは みんな同じ病気になる。
If you continue to rely on
the power of the Divine Tree,
you will all fall victim
to the same illness!
皆さんは
それでもいいんですか？
Are you okay with that?!
みんな こいつの話に
耳を貸すな！
Everyone!
Don't listen to this guy!
こいつらは忍宗の里から
やってきた連中だ。
These two came from
the Village of Ninshu!
世界をボロボロにしたあげくに→
They ravaged the world,
俺たちから神樹様まで
取り上げる気だ！
and now, they want to take
the Divine Tree from us!
そんなこと
させてたまるか！
We can't let them do that!
とっとと帰れ！
Get out of here!
神樹様がなくなったら
我々はどうなる？
What do you think would happen to us
if the Divine Tree was gone?!
さっさと出ていけ！
Get lost!
アシュラ逃げよう。
うう。
Ashura, let's get out of here!
(フタミ)大丈夫かな
インドラ様と アシュラ様は。
I hope Masters Indra and Ashura
are all right.
(ガマ丸)兄弟 いったい２人を
どんな場所にやったんじゃ？
Brother, what kind of places
did you send those two?
(ハゴロモ)簡単に言えば
同じ問題を抱えている村だ。
Simply put, villages burdened
with the same problem.
それを どう解決するのか
わしは それが知りたいのだ。
I want to know how they resolve it.
なるほどのう。
I see…
正直 もうどちらにするかは
決めているのか？
Be honest, have you already decided
which one will succeed you?
いいや 決めてはいない。
No, I haven't decided.
インドラは優秀だが すべてを
１人で解決しようと急ぎすぎる。
Indra's abilities
are extraordinary,
but he is too quick to try to
resolve everything by himself.
アシュラは
人に対する優しさがあるが→
Ashura is truly kind towards people,
but hesitates to take the lead.
なかなか
先頭に立とうとはしない。
２人が この旅で成長し→
If this trip helps them mature
and learn to support each other,
互いに支えあうように
なってくれれば→
文句はないのだがな。
I would have no complaints.
ガマ丸 何か
新しい夢でも見たか？
Gamamaru,
have you had a new dream?
２人の未来のことかのう？
About their futures?
見たら教えてほしいのかね？
If I did have a dream,
would you want me to tell you?
それは ズルじゃろ
後継者はお前が自分で決めんと。
That would be cheating.
You must name your successor
by yourself.
ゴホン。
よっこら。
さて わしは
そろそろ行くかのう。
Well then, I guess I'll be leaving.
ガマ丸 ２人のところに
行くつもりじゃないだろうな？
Gamamaru, I hope you're
not planning on visiting them…
ゲコ!?
余計なことはするなよ。
Don't interfere.
せんわ！
I won't!
しょせん お前たちでは
決断などできないようだな。
I doubt you all will ever
be able to reach a decision.
なあアシュラ
もう行こうぜ。
Come on Ashura, let's go.
これから気ままな旅に
出たっていいしよ。
Let's just go and have
a carefree journey.
う～ん。
Uh-huh…
そんなに気になるなら あの樹
こっそりぶっ壊しちまえよ！
If you're that concerned, just sneak
over there and destroy the tree.
そのくらい
お前の力でできるだろ！
You have the power to do that,
don't you?
でもそれじゃ
村の人たちがな。
But then, the villagers will…
苦しくはなるけど
いずれ死んじまうんだぜ。
They'll suffer sure,
but they're going to die eventually.
そうか そういえば
父上は神樹を→
Oh yeah…
Father didn't say to destroy
the Divine Tree.
ただ排除しろとは言わなかったな。
はあ？
Huh?
((インドラ アシュラ
お前たちは その地に向かい→
Indra… Ashura…
You will each go to these lands
(そこで起きている問題を
解決するのだ))
and settle whatever problem
has occurred there.
父上は 問題を解決しろ
と言ったんだ。
Father said to resolve the problem.
おいおい 何か変なこと
考えてんじゃねえだろうな？
Hey, hey… I hope you're
not getting any weird ideas.
解決するとしたら やっぱり
井戸を掘るしかないんだ。
To resolve the problem…
There's no other way
but to dig a well.
本気か？
長老が言ってたろ？
Are you serious?
You heard the old man.
岩が硬くて
井戸なんて掘れないって。
There's solid bedrock and
you can't dig a well.
ああ でも父上はあの時
こうも言ったんだ。
Yes… But that time, Father said…
((お前たちが授かった忍宗の力→
The power of Ninshu,
which you have inherited…
その使い方の手本は
どこにもない。
There is no handbook for its use.
Only you can decide how to use it.
(どう使うかは
お前たちの心しだいなのだ))
《俺たちしだい…》
It's up to us…
決めたぜ。
俺は自分の信じることをやる！
I've decided.
I'm going to do
what I believe is right!
はあ？
Huh?
何年かかろうと やり遂げる！
Even if it takes me years!
インドラ様だ！
It's Master Indra!
インドラ様が戻られたぞ！
Master Indra has returned!
さすがインドラ様だ。
もう戻ってきたのか？
Leave it to Master Indra!
He's back already?
ハァハァ よくぞご無事で。
I'm glad to see you well.
アシュラは？
いえ まだ…。
Where is Ashura?
He's not back yet.
そうか。
I see…
あの人は… まさか。
Is that—?
Don't tell me he's—?!
ハァハァハァ… アシュラ！
Ashura!
おう カンナ。
何やってるの!?
Oh, Kanna!
What are you doing?!
見りゃわかるだろ。
井戸掘ってるんだよ。
Can't you tell?
I'm digging a well.
ふぅ～。
本気なの？
あぁ 水さえ出れば→
Are you serious?
Yes.
If you have water, you won't have to
rely on the Divine Tree.
みんな神樹に頼らなくていいだろ。
無理だわ 村の人たちも
何年もかけて掘ったのよ。
That's impossible.
The villagers have tried
digging for years.
でも 水は出なかった。
And they've never found water.
俺も そう言ったさ。
I already told him that.
でも 言い出すと聞かないんだよ
こいつは。
But once he gets an idea,
he just won't listen.
できるか できないかは 関係ない。
It doesn't matter whether
it's possible or not.
俺は やるって決めたんだ。
I've decided to do it.
じゃあな カンナ。
See you, Kanna.
あんたたち… バカなの？
Are you two…stupid?
俺はともかく
あいつは間違いない。
I might be…
But he definitely is.
《何年かかろうと やり遂げる》
Even if it takes years,
I'll make it happen.
(インドラ)ただいま戻りました。
I've returned.
よく戻った。 で 首尾は？
Welcome back.
How did it go?
万事 仰せのとおりに。
I did exactly as I was told.
何か問題は？
Were there any problems?
ありません。
村には平穏が戻りました。
No.
Peace has returned to the village.
ハゴロモ様
インドラ様が先に戻られました。
Lord Hagoromo…
Master Indra has returned first.
ということは 忍宗の後継者は…。
Which means the successor
of Ninshu is…
いいや わしは
物事の速さを問うたのではない。
No, I'm not interested in
how fast things were resolved.
アシュラの帰りを待つ。
決めるのは それからだ。
I will wait for Ashura to return.
Then I will decide.
よいな インドラ。
はい。
Is that all right, Indra?
Yes.
(ゼツ)久しぶりだね インドラ。
It's been awhile, Indra.
あれ？ ノリが悪いね。
Oh?
You're in a bad mood.
僕に会いにきたんじゃないの？
Didn't you come to see me?
僕には全部わかってるよ。
I'm aware of everything, you know.
キミは ハゴロモの望むとおりにした。
You did exactly as Hagoromo wished.
But he's still not satisfied.
でも満足はしていない。
ハゴロモの思い描く忍宗の未来は
キミの思い描く未来じゃない。
The future Hagoromo envisions for
Ninshu is not the future you envision…
腕を上げたな。
You've improved.
俺たち２人は
どんなことがあろうと→
No matter what happens,
the two of us will follow you, Indra.
インドラ お前についていくぜ。
その言葉 胸に刻んでおく。
I will remember your words.
ハゴロモ様 すでに アシュラ様が
旅立って１年になります。
Lord Hagoromo…
It's been one year since Master Ashura
set out on his journey.
しかし いまだ
アシュラ様は戻ってきません。
But he still hasn't returned.
弟子たちの動揺もあります。
Your pupils are becoming restless.
そろそろ後継者を決められては。
Perhaps, you should
decide on a successor…
それは わかっている。
I realize that.
インドラ様なら
誰も文句を言いますまい。
No one will object to Master Indra.
なぜに アシュラ様の帰りを？
Why do you insist on waiting
for Master Ashura?
心配するな。
そろそろアシュラも戻ってくる頃だ。
Don't worry.
Ashura will return soon.
Lord Hagoromo!
ハゴロモ様！
なにごとだ？
What's going on?
インドラ様！
Master Indra!
Master Ashura has returned!
アシュラ様が… お帰りになりました。
お～い！
Hey!
アシュラ様だけではないぞ。
あんなに大勢？
It's not just Master Ashura!
There are so many with him!
タイゾウはわかるが
他の者は 何者なのだ？
I recognize Taizo,
but who are the others?
戻ってきたか。
So he's back.
(ガマ丸)自分の息子のことは
よくわかるのぉ。
You are astute about your own sons.
う～ん この水がめも
そろそろ限界かの。
I think this water jar
has seen its day.
いやいや 時間がかかった。
My, my, it took a long time.
弟のほうは
とんでもなく不器用じゃな。
The younger one is very clumsy…
根性は たいしたものじゃが。
But his tenacity
is quite something.
余計なことはするなと
念を押したはずだぞ。
I told you to mind
your own business.
しておらん。
ただ ずっと眺めとっただけじゃ。
I didn't do anything.
I just watched, that's all.
それより お前の耳に
入れておきたいことがある。
But I want to let you in
on something.
インドラの里のことじゃ。
About the village Indra went to.
おかえりなさいませ。
ただいま。 元気だったか？
Welcome back.
It's great to be home.
Have you been well?
はい。 アシュラ様こそ よくご無事で。
Yes. I'm glad you're well too,
Master Ashura.
さあ 早くハゴロモ様に。
Please go and see Lord Hagoromo.
えっ 兄さんに決まったんじゃ…。
What? Didn't he decide on
Elder Brother already?
まだ 父上は…。
Is Father still?
ずっと アシュラ様の帰りを
待っておられました。
He's been waiting all this time
for your return, Master Ashura.
そうなのか。
I see…
父上 ただいま戻りました。
Father, I've returned.
凛々しくなったな アシュラ。
You've become very dignified,
Ashura.
待ちわびたぞ。
We got tired waiting for you…
申し訳ありません 兄さん。
Forgive me Elder Brother.
With the level of my strength,
俺の力では 行った村の問題を
解決するには→
I needed much longer to resolve
the problem in the village.
長い時間が必要でした。
その者たちは？
Who are those people?
Oh, yes.
あっ はい。 村の方々です。
These are some of the villagers.
みんなが俺を助けてくれました。
They all helped me.
今では大事な仲間です。
And are now valuable friends.
この里の話を聞き
どうしても この目で見たくて→
We heard about this village,
and we wanted to see it,
アシュラさんとともにまいりました。
so we accompanied Master Ashura.
そうか。 よくいらした。
アシュラ 話を聞こう。
I see.
Welcome, good of you to come.
Ashura, let me hear your story.
俺の行った村は
神樹の水源に頼っていました。
The village I went to relied on
the Divine Tree's water source.
そこで
井戸を掘ることにしたんです。
So I decided to dig a well.
((ハァ ハァ…。
アシュラ 本気で井戸を掘ってるの？
Ashura! Are you seriously
digging a well?
俺は そう決めたんだ。
It's what I've decided.
はぁ～。
ふぅ…。
ん？
なんだよ… また 俺たちに
石を投げにきたのか!?
What the hell?
Are they back to throw rocks at us?
待て！
Wait.
あんたたち…。
You guys…
俺たちも手伝う。
We'll help you.
自分たちのことくらい
自分でやりたい。
We want to do it because
it's for our village.
できれば 俺たちにも
忍宗を教えてくれないか？
If you can,
could you teach us Ninshu too?
あ… うん。
Uh-huh!
みんな！ 静かにしてくれ。
Everyone, please be quiet!
どうしたんだ？ アシュラ！
What's the matter, Ashura?
聞こえないか？ 音がする！
Can you hear it?
That sound…
水だ！
どうした!?
It's water!
– What is it?
– What happened?
これって…。
This is—!
– Water!
– We hit water!
(タイゾウ)やった！ やったぞ!!
– We did it!
やったわ アシュラ！
あぁ やった！
You did it, Ashura!
We did it!
(アシュラ)やった～！
母さん…。
Mom…
カンナ。
Kanna.
母さん！
Mom!
今こそ 我々は
長き呪縛より解き放たれる。
We are finally free from the curse.
I see…
そうか… お前の広めた忍宗が
人々を救ったか。
はい！
では これより
忍宗の後継者を発表する。
忍宗の後継者は…。